Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
- Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1837-1870 (Box 7-12A)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 8, Folder 64-96)
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-16-1866-07-20 (Box 8, Folder 81)
      - W. C. Park to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-16; Park, W. C. (Box 8, Folder 81)
        W. C. Park asks Robert E. Lee if Professor Maximilian Schele de Vere is teaching at Washington College.
        Schele de Vere, M. (Maximilian), 1820-1898
      - Andrew Jackson Moses Jr. to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-16; Moses, A. J. (Andrew Jackson), b. ca.1847-1911 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Andrew Jackson Moses asks Robert E. Lee about attending Washington College.
      - J. Ditzler to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-17; Ditzler, J. (Box 8, Folder 81)
        J. Ditzler asks Robert E. Lee how he can contact Professor Albert Taylor Bledsoe. He also offers to lecture at Washington College and send Lee a copy of his history book.
        Military history; Philosophy; Theology; Bledsoe, Albert Taylor, 1809-1877
      - Caroline Wright Jones to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-17; Jones, Caroline Wright (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Mrs. Joseph Jones (Caroline Wright) invites Robert E. Lee to Warren County on August 8th for the unveiling of a memorial for his daughter Anne Carter Lee.
        North Carolina -- Warren County; Lee, Anne Carter, 1839-1862
      - William Greenleaf Rolfe to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-17; Rolfe, W. G. (William Greenleaf), 1826-1909 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        William Greenleaf Rolfe asks Robert E. Lee for information on Washington College and Virginia Military Institute for potential students in Ashley County, Arkansas.
        Arkansas--Ashley County
      - Mary Hardaway to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-18; Hardaway, Mary (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Mary Hardaway asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - George J. Hobday to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-18; Hobday, George J. (George Jonadab), 1847-ca.1927 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        George J. Hobday asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - William A. Rogers to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-18; Rogers, William A., ca.1820-d.1881 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        William A. Rogers asks Robert E. Lee if students of Washington College may begin after the official start date of academic terms. He also asks for the address of Charles R. Jones.
        Jones, Charles R., b. ca. 1845
      - Mary C. Allen to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-18; Allen, Mary C. (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Mary C. Allen asks Robert E. Lee about sending her sons to Washington College.
      - Albert Jefer Montgomery to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-18; Montgomery, A. J. (Albert Jefer), b. ca. 1844 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Albert Jefer Montgomery asks about attending Washington College. He notes that he is a veteran of the Confederate States Army.
      - Delaware B. Kemper to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-19; Kemper, Delaware B. "Del", 1833-1899 (Box 8, Folder 81)
        Delaware B. Kemper shares that he is applying for professorship at Hampden-Sydney College and they have asked for his military references. He asks President Lee if he can give a reference.
        Hampden-Sydney College
      - W. A. Wash to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-20; Wash, W. A. (Box 8, Folder 81)
        W. A. Wash asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-21-1866-07-23 (Box 8, Folder 82)
      - Duff Green to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-21; Green, Duff, 1791-1875 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        Duff Green writes to Robert E. Lee that he plans to send his grandson, Benjamin Green Maynard, to Washington College.
        Maynard, Benjamin G. (Benjamin Green), b. ca. 1848
      - Wade Hampton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-21; Hampton, Wade, 1818-1902 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        Wade Hampton informs Robert E. Lee that he has gathered data from his old officers for Lee's paper on the American Civil War.
        Military history
      - J. W. Heatley to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-22; Heatley, J. W., b. ca. 1849 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        J. W. Heatley asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - Walter O. Bullock to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; Bullock, Waller O. (Waller Overton), 1842-1903 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        Waller O. Bullock asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - A. J. Frantz to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; Frantz, A. J. (Box 8, Folder 82)
        A. J. Frantz sends Robert E. Lee an advertisement for advertising space in the Brandon Republican newspaper Rankin County, Mississippi.
        Advertising; Mississippi--Rankin County; The Brandon Republican
      - Thomas Treadwell Eaton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; Eaton, T. T. (Thomas Treadwell), 1845-1907 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        Thomas Treadwell Eaton asks Robert E. Lee if he can attend the Washington College Fall term in 1866. He also asks if he can secure places for friends Adelbert Smith and William H. Washington.
        Smith, Adelbert
      - John T. Harrison to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; Harrison, John T. (Box 8, Folder 82)
        John T. Harrison informs Robert E. Lee that he is behind in the Latin and Greek requirements for Washington College admission and asks about preparatory schools.
      - George Anderson Mayse to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; Mayse, George Anderson, 1826-1903 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        George Anderson Mayse invites Robert E. Lee to Warm Springs, VA for the summer season.
        Virginia -- Warm Springs
      - Alexander McKinley to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; McKinley, Alexander (Box 8, Folder 82)
        Alexander McKinley asks Robert E. Lee about entering his son into Washington College.
      - R. M. McClellan to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-23; McClellan, R. M. (Box 8, Folder 82)
        R. M. McClellan introduces Washington College student David L. Anderson to President Lee. He explains that Anderson is behind in Greek and suggests that he be enrolled in that class.
        Anderson, David L.
      - Samuel Wethered to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07; Wethered, Samuel, 1814-1874 (Box 8, Folder 82)
        This letter was written sometime in July 1866. Lee responded on July 23rd, 1866. Samuel Wethered inquires about sending his son to Washington College.
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-24-1866-07-25 (Box 8, Folder 83)
      - James Springfield Edwards to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-24; Edwards, J. S. (James Springfield) (Box 8, Folder 83)
        James Springfield Edwards asks for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - John Edward Burson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-24; Burson, John Edward (Box 8, Folder 83)
        John Edward Burson requests a catalogue of Washington College. He also asks about boarding and the potential for other students from his community accompanying him to school in Lexington.
      - Richard Sears McCulloh to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-24; McCulloh, R. S. (Richard Sears), 1818-1894 (Box 8, Folder 83)
        Professor Richard Sears McCulloh, writing from New York City and having consulted with architects, sends a basic floor plan, specifications, and cost estimates for the contruction of a chapel at Washington College.
        Lee Chapel (Washington and Lee University); Architecture; Church architecture; University Chapel (Washington and Lee University); Architecture, Gothic
      - Benjamin Franklin French to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-24; French, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1799-1877 (Box 8, Folder 83)
        Benjamin Franklin French offers resources for Lee's planned book on the history of the American Civil War.
      - Gabriel James Rains to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-24; Rains, Gabriel James, 1803-1881 (Box 8, Folder 83)
        Gabriel James Rains wishes to leave Summerville Institute to teach at Virginia Military Institute (V.M.I.). Rains mistakenly suggests that Lee is presiding over V.M.I. rather than Washington College.
        Summerville Institute; Virginia Military Institute
      - Jesse W. Shanks, 1866-07-24; Shanks, Jesse W. (Box 8, Folder 83)
        Jesse Shanks inquires about sending his brother to Washington College.
      - William A. Brown to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-25; Brown, W. A. (William A.), b. ca. 1849 (Box 8, Folder 83)
        William A. Brown asks Robert E. Lee for a catalogue of Washington College.
      - R. M. McClellan to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-25; McClellan, R. M. (Box 8, Folder 83)
        R. M. McClellan introduces admitted Washignton College student William W. Collins to Robert E. Lee and suggests that Collins shoudl enrroll in a preparatory Greek course.
        Collins, William W.
      - W. R. Abbott to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-25; Abbott, W. R. (Box 8, Folder 83)
        W. R. Abbott announces Robert E. Lee's election to the Educational Asssociation of Virginia.
        Educational Association of Virginia
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-26-1866-07-27 (Box 8, Folder 84)
      - H. A. (Hampton A) Rice to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-27; Rice, H. A. (Hampton A.), 1840-1884 (Box 8, Folder 84)
        H. A. (Hampton A.) Rice asks for a catalogue or a list of expenses for attending Washington College for potential students in Macon. On the back of this letter Rice asks for a catalog to be sent to H. L. (Hampton Lea) Jarnagin Jr.
        Mississippi--Macon; Jernigan, H. L. (Hampton Lea), Jr., 1848-1882
      - Charles A. (Charles Alfred) Welch to Robert E. Lee, 1866-07-27; Welch, Charles A. (Charles Alfred), Sr., 1815-1908 (Box 8, Folder 84)
        Charles A. (Charles Alfred) Welch asks when his son, Francis Welch, should come to Washington College for examination. Welch also asks if there are uniform or clothing regulations that his son must follow.
        Welch asks that Lee addresses his response to Sohier and Welch of Boston Massachussetts.
        Welch, Francis C. (Francis Clarke), 1850-1919; Sohier and Welch
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-28-1866-07-30 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Correspondences, 1866-07-31 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-01-1866-08-03 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-06 (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-07-1866-08-08 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-09-1866-08-10 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-11-1866-08-14 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-15-1866-08-18 (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-20 (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-21-1866-08-23 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-25-1866-08-27 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Correspondences, 1866-08-28-1866-08-31 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 8A, Folder 97-120)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 9, Folder 121-155)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 9A, Folder 156-179)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 10, Folder 180-207)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 10A, Folder 208-229)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 11, Folder 230-254)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 11A, Folder 255-284)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 12, Folder 285-305)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee (Box 12A, Folder 306-321)
- Reminiscences and Obituaries for Robert E. Lee (Box 13)
  - Control Folder (Box 13, Folder 0)
  - Notebook - William Allan's "Memoranda of a Conversation with Robert E. Lee", 1868-02-16-1870-02-19; 1886-11; Gordon, E. C. (Edward Clifford), 1842 - 1922; Allan, William, 1837-1889 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Between February 1868 and February 1870 Washington College professor and former Confederate Ordinance officer, William Allan, had five conversations with college president Robert E. Lee which he manually recorded in this memo book which he titled "Conversations with Gen. R. E. Lee". Soon after each conversation, Allan described retreating to his office to record the highlights. In 1886, former Washington College Clerk of faculty and Librarian, Edward Clifford "E.C." Gordon shared with Allan, by mail, a similar manuscript reminiscence of a discussion he had with Lee in 1868 on the Sharpsburg/Antietam campaign, specifically the story of Lee's "Lost Dispatch". Allan transcribed Gordon's reminiscence into his memo book – with a background note. (Gordon's original reminiscence was then purportedly returned to him.) The memo book is accompanied by an informative 1886 letter from Gordon to Allan on the Lee conversations. There are also two letters regarding the gift of the memoranda book to Washington and Lee University in 1946 by Mrs. Louisa P. Allan, William Allan's daughter – in – law. Subjects of the conversations include Lee's objectives and strategy at different points during the American Civil War; Lee's decision to resign from the United States Army on April 20, 1861 including his conversations with U.S. Army General Winfield Scott; and commentary, at times critical, of Federal and Confederate generals and leaders including George McClellan, D.H. Hill, James Longstreet, Jefferson Davis, Richard Ewell, Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson, Joseph Johnston, J.E.B. Stuart, and John-Fitz Porter. Civil War battles mentioned or discussed include Antietam, Fredericksburg, Gaines Mill and the Seven Days Battles, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, and the fall of the defenses at Petersburg, Va.
    Chancellorsville, Battle of (Virginia: 1863); Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Hill, D. H. (Daniel Harvey); Ewell, Richard Stoddert, 1817-1872; Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston); Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866; Porter, Fitz-John, 1822-1901
  - Magazine - "The Land We Love", 1868-02; Hill, D. H. (Daniel Harvey); Campbell, J. L. (John Lyle) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Robert E. Lee's copy of D.H. Hill's post Civil War magazine "The Land We Love," which published an article pertaining to the story of Lee's "Lost Dispatch" - an order by General Robert E. Lee directing movements of his Army of Northern Virginia during the Maryland Campaign of 1862. It was lost by an unidentified Confederate courier and found by Union soldiers and subsequently forwarded to Union General George B. McClellan. The contents of the dispatch influenced the battles of South Mountain and Antietam.
    Maryland Campaign (1862); Campbell, J. L. (John Lyle)
  - Correspondences, 1886-11-18; 1946-09-27 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Letter from E.C.(Edward Clifford)Gordon, former Washington College Clerk of Faculty, to Col. William Allan of th eMcDonough institute in Baltimore, Md. and former mathematics professor at Washington College between 1866 and 1873 regarding an accompanying memo book in which Gordon documented a long conversation he had with Robert E. Lee on February 16, 1868. A main theme of the letter is the content from the memo book regarding the story of Lee's "Lost Dispatch" during his Maryland Campaign of 1862. The second letter accompanied the memo book when it was given by Louisa P. Allan, Col. William Allan's daughter - in - law, to Washington and Lee University President Francis Pendleton Gaines in 1946.
  - Reminiscences - Authors: B-J, 1900-1960; Bond, Christiana; Bailey, William Whitman, 1843 - 1914; Campbell, Henry Donald; Hobson, John P. (John Peyton), 1850-1934; Chester, Samuel H.; Cooke, Giles B.; Johnston, William Preston; Dixon, Frank McClung, 1900-1980; Denison, George T. (George Taylor), 1839-1925; Jones, Carter H., Dr. (Carter Helm), 1861-1946; Joynes, Edward S. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Reminiscences of Robert E. Lee including manuscripts, typescripts, newspaper clippings, and published materials by subjects with surnames begininng with letters B through J. See agents list for authors.
    Bruce, George S., 1859 - ?; Bruce, Sarah Helen, 1860 - 1955; Dixon, Frank McClung, 1900-1980; Barbour, Edward Alexander, 1859-1937
  - Reminiscences - Authors: K-Z, 1865-1960; McCorkle, Emmett W., Dr., 1855-1938; Norfleet, Thomas S. (Thomas Spruill), 1849-1942; Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1825-1893; Lee, George Taylor, 1848-1933; Lacy, John Alexander, 1850-1923; Signaigo, Augustine John, II, 1861-1943 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Reminiscences of Robert E. Lee including manuscripts, typescripts, newspaper clippings, and published materials by subjects with surnames begininng with letters K through Z. See agents list for authors.
    McRae, David; Randolph, Mary Henry T. (Mary Henry Taylor), 1859-1935; Vaughan, James English, 1846-
  - Reminiscences: Story of Finding Lee's Coffin, no date (Box 13, Folder e)
  - Lee's Hair (Box 13, Folder f)
  - Papers fom Lee's desk and sideboard, no date (Box 13, Folder j)
  - Funeral obsequies and will of Robert E. Lee, no date (Box 13, Folder k)
  - Flowers from Lee's casket, no date (Box 13, Folder l)
  - Printed Obituaries, no date (Box 13, Folder m)
  - Centennial Observance of Lee's Death, no date (Box 13, Folder n)
- Letters from Robert E. Lee Family Members (Box 14A-14B, Folder 1-97)
  The core of this series is comprised of letters written by members of Robert E. Lee's immediate family, though it includes letters from some more distant relatives and descendants.
  - Letters from Lee Family (Box 14A, Folder 1-54)
  - Letters from Lee Family (Box 14B, Folder 55-97)
- Lee Family Printed Material (Box 15)
- Scrapbooks about Robert E. Lee, 1870-1920 (Box 16)
  Two oversize scrapbooks commemorating the life of Robert E. Lee. Both scrapbooks contain voluminous amounts of newspaper clippings, some pamphlets and published materials, manuscript and typescript documents, and printed Lee imagery. The compiler of each scrapbook is unknown.
- Student information Cards, 1865-1873 (Box 17)
  Typescript notecards created during the 1940s with information on students who attended Washington College's undergraduate and law school during Robert E. Lee's presidency. Details included were, for the most part, limited to hometown (town, state) and current location at the time that the original information was gathered. This information was copied in the 1940s likely from some original list, perhaps from the Washington and Lee University alumni catalog of 1888.
- Robert E. Lee Memorbilia (Box 18-19)
  - Lee Memorabilia (Box 19)
    - Control Folder (Box 19, Folder 0)
    - Amnesty Resolutions, no date (Box 19A, Folder 1)
    - "A Book for Gen.Lee" by G. B. Johnston, no date (Box 19A, Folder 3)
    - Civil War, no date (Box 19A, Folder 4)
    - Civil War and Reconstruction, no date (Box 19A, Folder 5)
    - Commemorations and Addresses, no date (Box 19A, Folder 6)
    - Lee Family, no date (Box 19A, Folder 7)
    - Friends of Lee, no date (Box 19A, Folder 8)
    - Lee Homes, no date (Box 19A, Folder 9)
    - Lee Chapel, no date (Box 19A, Folder 10)
    - LEE-ANNA, A Catalogue of the Collection of R. E. Lee, no date (Box 19A, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Magazines, no date (Box 19A, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, no date (Box 19A, Folder 13)
  - Lee Memorabilia (Box 19B)
    - Plays, no date (Box 19B, Folder 14)
    - Poems, no date (Box 19B, Folder 15)
    - Portraits, no date (Box 19B, Folder 16)
    - Sheet Music, no date (Box 19B, Folder 17)
    - Southern Historical Society, no date (Box 19B, Folder 18)
    - Speeches, no date (Box 19B, Folder 19)
    - Traveller, no date (Box 19B, Folder 20)
    - Washington College, no date (Box 19B, Folder 21)
    - Section of Lee statue crate, no date (Box 19B, Folder 22)
- Letters and Information about the Robert E. Lee Papers (Box 20A-21)
  - Letters and Information about the Robert E. Lee Papers (Box 20A)
  - Letters and Information about the Robert E. Lee Papers (Box 20B)
  - Letters and Information about the Robert E. Lee Papers (Box 20C)
  - Letters and Information about the Robert E. Lee Papers (Box 21)
- Commemorative Pamphlets on Robert E. Lee (Box 22-26)
  - Lee Pamphlets (Box 22)
  - Lee Pamphlets (Box 23)
  - Lee Pamphlets (Box 24)
  - Lee Pamphlets (Box 25)
  - Lee Pamphlets (Box 26)
- Robert E. Lee Photographs and Prints (Box 27-27A)
  - Robert E. Lee Photographs and Prints (Box 27)
  - Robert E. Lee Photographs and Prints (Box 27A)